A Finding Aid to the Charles Searles Papers, 1953-2010, in the Archives of American Art AAA.searchar
Archives of American Art
Charles Searles papers
1953-2010
AAA.searchar
Archives of American Art
3.9 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor and painter Charles Searles measure 3.9 linear feet and date from 1953 to 2010. The collection documents his career through scattered biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, printed material, artwork, photographs, and a scrapbook.
Searles, Charles Robert, 1937-2004
Related Archival Materials note
Also at the Archives of American Art is an interview with Charles Searles conducted on June 13, 1991, by Cynthia Veloric, for the Archives of American Art Philadelphia Project.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of sculptor and painter Charles Searles measure 3.9 linear feet and date from 1953 to 2010. The collection documents his career through scattered biographical material, correspondence, personal business records, printed material, artwork, photographs, and a scrapbook.
Scattered biographical material includes legal papers, address books, transcripts, and awards. Correspondence includes correspondence with galleries, museums, and organizations. Personal business records consist of Searles' files on commissions, exhibitions, workshops and programs, and employment contracts. Printed material includes exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, as well as printed material of interest to Searles, but not directly documenting his career. Artwork consists of sketches, designs, flyers, a portrait of Kathleen Spicer by Russell Gordon, and a portrait of Searles by K. Spicer. Photographs depict Searles, Searles' artwork, and artist Walt Edmonds. Scrapbooks consist of news clippings and loose material that was originally inserted in between the pages in no particular order.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2012 by Kathleen Spicer Searles, Charles Searles' widow.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1963-2004 (0.5 linear ft.; Boxes 1, 6)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1956-2004 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1969-2007 (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 1-2,6)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1953-2010 (1.4 linear feet; Boxes 3-4, 6)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1980s-2000 (9 folders; Box 5)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1964-2000 (3 folders; Box 5)
Series 7: Scrapbooks, circa 1970s-2005 (0.3 linear ft.; Box 6)
Biographical/Historical note
Charles Robert Searles (1937-2004) was a sculptor, painter and muralist in Philadelphia, Pa. and New York, N.Y. Searles attended the University of Pennsylvania and graduated from the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts in 1972. He was influenced by African art after traveling to Nigeria on the Ware Memorial Traveling Scholarship during his studies at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts. During his career he participated in over 100 exhibitions in Denmark, Nigeria, and throughout the United States.
Searles taught art at several institutions including the Pratt Institute, the University of the Arts (Philadelphia College of Art), and the Philadephia Museum of Art. He also completed commission work for Newark Station, PATCO (Port Authority Transit Corporation), and MTA (Metropolitan Transportation Authority).
Searles moved to New York, NY in 1978 where he spent most of his career. He was married to artist Kathleen Spicer until his death on November 27, 2004.
Edmonds, Walt; Gordon, Russell Talbert, 1936-; Spicer, Kathleen; Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Muralists--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Sculptors--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia; Sketches; Transcripts
- Biographical Material, 1963-2004; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 1, 6
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes two address books, interview transcripts, artist statements and writings by Searles, academic papers on Searles' artwork, certificates and awards, blueprints and documents for Searles' home in upstate New York, and legal documents pertaining to disputes between the tenants of 640 Broadway and management.
  - Address Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Interview Transcripts, Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Papers, Artist Statements, Notes, circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1963-2003; Oversize material housed in Box 6, Folder 7. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - House Upstate N.Y., 1990-1999; 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - 640 Rental Agreements, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Legal, 640 Broadway Loft Board, circa 1984-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Lawsuits, 640 Broadway, circa 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 11-16)
  - Lawsuits, 640 Broadway Leak, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Heller Realty Documents, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Legal, City of Philadelphia, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Oversize Certificates and Awards from Box 1, Folder 5, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1956-2004; Series 2; 5 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence consists of letters regarding exhibitions, teaching, and art related subjects. Searles maintained a separate file for gallery and museum correspondence, but correspondence with galleries and musuems can also be found in the general correspondence.
  - General Correspondence, 1956-2004 (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
  - Galleries and Museums, 1975-1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Personal Business Records, 1968-2007; Series 3; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 6
  Personal business records document Searles' commissions, exhibitions, workshops, employment contracts, and other activities. Records are filed by name of organization, museum, gallery, or project and may include correspondence, notes, printed materials, contracts, and invoices.
  - 2nd World Black-African Festival Program, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Afro-American Historical Museum Exhibition, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Balch Institute Exhibition, circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Brooklyn Sculpture Commission, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Bryn Mawr College, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Commission Proposals, circa 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dallas Museum of Art Exhibition, 1989-1991; Oversize material housed in Box 6, Folder 8. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Dempsey Center Harlem Commission, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - First District P.A. Commission, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - G.S.A. Mural Contract-Commission, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Herbert Johnson Museum N.Y. Exhibition, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Howard Univ., D.C. Exhibition, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ile-Ife Museum, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - June Kelly Gallery Exhibition, 1993-2007 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Kentucky State Univ., Frankfort, K.Y. Exhibition, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mallory Playground Mural Commission, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Merabash Museum, Henderson, N.J. Exhibition, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Art Organizations, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Universities, 1969-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - MTA Jamaica St. Commission, 1995-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National Center of Afro-American Artists Exhibition, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National Conference of Artists Membership, circa 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Newark Station Arts Commission, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - PATCO Commission, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Art, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Philadelphia College of Art, Employment Contracts, 1973-1994 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, Div. Education, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, Urban Outreach, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Playground P.A. Richert Commission, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Ryno Fab, circa 1992-1997 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sande Webster Gallery Exhibition, 1984-2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - State Museum, Harrisburg, P.A. Exhibition, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Studio Museum, Harlem, N.Y., 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - U. of South Alabama, Sales, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - West Philly Library Commission, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Whitney Museum, N.Y. Exhibition, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Workshops and Programs, 1989-1992; circa 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - Oversize Dallas Museum of Art Exhibition from Box 1, Folder 33, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Printed Material, 1953-2010; Series 4; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 6
  Printed materials consists of flyers, calendars, magazines and journals, exhibition announcements, posters, and catalogs that were of interest to or feature Searles. Printed material also includes a collection of published cartoons by Gerald 2X compiled by Searles, Bebe's Kids Teleplay by Reginald Hudlin, and memorabilia.
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1973-2010 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Exhibition Posters, 1984; 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1969-2009 (Box 3, Folder 6-12)
  - Flyers, circa 1978-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Calendars, 1989; 1993; Oversize material housed in Box 6, Folder 9 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bebe's Kids Teleplay, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Memorabilia, circa 1953-1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Magazines and Journals, 1968-1979; 1992-2005; 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Cartoons by Gerald 2X, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Calendar from Box 3, Folder 14, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Artwork, circa 1980-2000; Series 5; 9 Folders Box 5
  Artwork consists of pencil and ink drawings, flyers, doodles, designs, mixed media works, and reproductions of works by Searles. Artwork includes a pencil drawing of Searles by K. Spicer, and a pencil drawing of Kathleen Spicer by Russell Gordon.
  - Pencil Drawing of Charles Searles by K. Spicer, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Pencil Drawing of Kathleen Spicer by Russell Gordon, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ink Drawings, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pencil Drawings, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Designs, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Doodles, circa 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mixed Media, 1983; 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Flyers by Charles Searles, circa 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Reproductions, circa 2000 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Photographs, 1964-2000; Series 6; 3 Folders Box 5
  Found here are two photographs of Searles, one group photograph with Searles at the University of Pennsylvania in 1964, a small group of photographs of Searles' artwork, and one photograph of artist Walt Edmonds.
  - Photographs of Charles Searles, circa 1964-2000 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1995; 1974 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Photograph of Walt Edmonds, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Scrapbook, 1970-2005; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 6
  One scrapbook consists of 21 pages that were removed from a binder as well as loose material that was originally inserted in between the scrapbook pages in no particular order. The scrapbook consists mainly of newspaper and magazine clippings documenting Searles' career.
  - Scrapbook, circa 1970-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Loose Material from Scrapbook, circa 1970-2005 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)